<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-whats-new'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>What's New in OpenAM <?eval ${project.version}?></title>

 <para>OpenAM <?eval ${project.version}?> fixes a number of issues, and
 provides the following additional features.</para>
 
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>The Universal Gateway is a high-performance reverse proxy server with
   specialized session management and credential replay functionality. The
   Universal Gateway may run as a standalone simple single sign-on solution,
   or be integrated with an existing web access management system. With either
   method, there is no need to modify the target application or the container
   that it runs in.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The universal fedlet includes federation capabilities in the
   gateway, enabling federation capabilities for applications that cannot be
   modified to use the Fedlet and SAML 2.0.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now handles Active Directory password expiration responses
   properly. Setup wizards make it easier to use OpenLDAP and OpenDJ as
   the identity repository.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>SAML 2.0 extensions let the system handle situations more flexibly.
   For example, the extensions let the system handle situations that arise
   when the identity provider receives failed an authentication request and so
   must skip some processing, or when there remains additional interaction
   with the user after a completed assertion but before providing
   authorization.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>A new, beta session failover mechanism introduces a replacement for
   the existing implementation that relies on Message Queue and Berkeley DB
   with a highly scalable, pure Java implementation.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Improvements in the upgrade process streamline the move to the
   new version.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports YubiKey authentication. The YubiKey simplifies
   the process of logging in with a One Time Password token as it does not
   require the user to re-type long pass codes from a display device into the
   login field of the computer. The YubiKey is inserted in the USB-port of any
   computer and the OTP is generated and automatically entered with a simple
   touch of a button on the YubiKey, and without the need of any client
   software or drivers.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports adaptive risk authentication. You configure the
   adaptive risk authentication module to assess risks, and then you add the
   module into an authentication chain. The module determines whether to
   require further authentication processing based on assessment of the risk
   involved during authentication. Adaptive risk authentication lets you
   require more from users when they login from an unfamiliar location, from
   a new device, after a long period during which the account remained idle,
   and so forth.</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 
</chapter>

